neovim-flake-manual
  |   |  Next

neovim-flake-manual

Version release-v0.6

Table of Contents

Preface
Try it out
Custom Configuration
Custom Neovim Package
Custom Plugins

New Method
Old Method
Configuring

Default Configs

Maximal
Nix
Tidal Cycles

Home Manager
Language Support

LSP Custom Packages/Command

Hacking neovim-flake

Getting Started
Guidelines
Testing Changes
Keybinds
Adding Plugins

A. Neovim Flake Configuration Options

Preface

If you noticed a bug caused by neovim-flake then please consider reporting it over the neovim-flake issue tracker. Bugfixes, feature additions and upstreamed changes are welcome over the neovim-flake pull requests tab.

Try it out

Table of Contents

Using Prebuilt Configs

Thanks to the portability of Nix, you can try out neovim-flake without actually installing it to your machine. Below are the commands you may run to try out different configurations provided by this flake. As of v0.5, three configurations are provided:

Nix

Tidal

Maximal

You may try out any of the provided configurations using the nix run command on a system where Nix is installed.

$ cachix use neovim-flake # Optional: it'll save you CPU resources and time
$ nix run github:notashelf/neovim-flake#nix # will run the default minimal configuration

Do keep in mind that this is susceptible to garbage collection meaning it will be removed from your Nix store once you garbage collect. If you wish to install neovim-flake, please take a look at custom-configuration or home-manager sections for installation instructions.

Using Prebuilt Configs

Available Configs

$ nix run github:notashelf/neovim-flake#nix
$ nix run github:notashelf/neovim-flake#tidal
$ nix run github:notashelf/neovim-flake#maximal

Available Configs

Nix

Nix configuration by default provides LSP/diagnostic support for Nix alongisde a set of visual and functional plugins. By running nix run ., which is the default package, you will build Neovim with this config.

Tidal

Tidal is an alternative config that adds vim-tidal on top of the plugins from the Nix configuration.

Maximal

Maximal is the ultimate configuration that will enable support for more commonly used language as well as additional complementary plugins. Keep in mind, however, that this will pull a lot of dependencies.

You are strongly recommended to use the binary cache if you would like to try the Maximal configuration.

Custom Configuration

Custom configuration is done with the neovimConfiguration while using the flake as a standalone package. It takes in the configuration as a module. The output of the configuration function is an attrset.

{
  options = "The options that were available to configure";
  config = "The outputted configuration";
  pkgs = "The package set used to evaluate the module";
  neovim = "The built neovim package";
}

The following is an example of a barebones vim configuration with the default theme enabled.

{
  inputs.neovim-flake = {
    url = "github:notashelf/neovim-flake";
    inputs.nixpkgs.follows = "nixpkgs";
  };

  outputs = {nixpkgs, neovim-flake, ...}: let
    system = "x86_64-linux";
    pkgs = nixpkgs.legacyPackages.${system};
    configModule = {
      # Add any custom options (and feel free to upstream them!)
      # options = ...

      config.vim = {
        theme.enable = true;
      };
    };

    customNeovim = neovim-flake.lib.neovimConfiguration {
      modules = [configModule];
      inherit pkgs;
    };
  in {
    # this will make the package available as a flake input
    packages.${system}.neovim = customNeovim.neovim;

    # this is an example nixosConfiguration using the built neovim package
    nixosConfigurations = {
      yourHostName = nixpkgs.lib.nixosSystem {
        # ...
        modules = [
          ./configuration.nix # or whatever your configuration is

          # this will make wrapped neovim available in your system packages
          {environment.systemPackages = [customNeovim.neovim];}
        ];
        # ...
      };
    };
  };
}

Your built neovim configuration can be exposed as a flake output, or be added to your system packages to make it available across your system. You may also consider passing the flake output to home-manager to make it available to a specific user without using the home-manager module.

Custom Neovim Package

As of v0.5, you may now specify the neovim package that will be wrapped with your configuration. This is done with the vim.package option.

{inputs, pkgs, ...}: {
  # using the neovim-nightly overlay
  config.vim.package = inputs.neovim-overlay.packages.${pkgs.system}.neovim;
}

The neovim-nightly-overlay always exposes an unwrapped package. If using a different source, you are highly recommended to get an “unwrapped” version of the neovim package,similar to neovim-unwrapped in nixpkgs.

Custom Plugins

You can use custom plugins, before they are implemented in the flake. To add a plugin, you need to add it to your config’s config.vim.startPlugins array.

Table of Contents

New Method
Old Method
Configuring

New Method

As of version 0.5, we have a more extensive API for configuring plugins, under vim.extraPlugins.

Instead of using DAGs exposed by the library, you may use the extra plugin module as follows:

{
  config.vim.extraPlugins = with pkgs.vimPlugins; {
    aerial = {
      package = aerial-nvim;
      setup = ''
        require('aerial').setup {
          -- some lua configuration here
        }
      '';
    };

    harpoon = {
      package = harpoon;
      setup = "require('harpoon').setup {}";
      after = ["aerial"];
    };
  };
}

Old Method

Users who have not yet updated to 0.5, or prefer a more hands-on approach may use the old method where the load order of the plugins is determined by DAGs.

{
  # fetch plugin source from GitHub and add it to startPlugins
  config.vim.startPlugins = [
    (pkgs.fetchFromGitHub {
      owner = "FrenzyExists";
      repo = "aquarium-vim";
      rev = "d09b1feda1148797aa5ff0dbca8d8e3256d028d5";
      sha256 = "CtyEhCcGxxok6xFQ09feWpdEBIYHH+GIFVOaNZx10Bs=";
    })
  ];
}

Configuring

Just making the plugin to your neovim configuration available might not always be enough. In that case, you can write custom vimscript or lua config, using config.vim.configRC or config.vim.luaConfigRC respectively. These options are attribute sets, and you need to give the configuration you’re adding some name, like this:

{
  # this will create an "aquarium" section in your init.vim with the contents of your custom config
  # which will be *appended* to the rest of your configuration, inside your init.vim
  config.vim.configRC.aquarium = "colorscheme aquiarum";
}

Note

If your configuration needs to be put in a specific place in the config, you can use functions from inputs.neovim-flake.lib.nvim.dag to order it. Refer to https://github.com/nix-community/home-manager/blob/master/modules/lib/dag.nix to find out more about the DAG system.

Also, if you successfully made your plugin work, please make a PR to add it to the flake, or open an issue with your findings so that we can make it available for everyone easily.

Default Configs

While you can configure neovim-flake yourself using the builder, you can also use the pre-built configs that are available. Here are a few default configurations you can use.

Table of Contents

Maximal
Nix
Tidal Cycles

Maximal

$ nix shell github:notashelf/neovim-flake#maximal test.nix

It is the same fully configured neovim as with the Nix config, but with every supported language enabled.

::: note Running the maximal config will download a lot of packages as it is downloading language servers, formatters, and more. :::

Nix

$ nix run github:notashelf/neovim-flake#nix test.nix

Enables all the of neovim plugins, with language support for specifically Nix. This lets you see what a fully configured neovim setup looks like without downloading a whole bunch of language servers and associated tools.

Tidal Cycles

$ nix run github:notashelf/neovim-flake#tidal file.tidal

Utilizing vim-tidal and mitchmindtree’s fantastic tidalcycles.nix start playing with tidal cycles in a single command.

In your tidal file, type a cycle e.g. d1 $ s "drum" and then press ctrl+enter. Super collider with superdirt, and a modified GHCI with tidal will start up and begin playing. Note, you need jack enabled on your system. If you are using pipewire, its as easy as setting services.pipewire.jack.enable = true in your configuration.

Home Manager

The Home Manager module allows us to customize the different vim options from inside the home-manager configuration and it is the preferred way of configuring neovim-flake, both on NixOS and non-NixOS systems.

To use it, we first add the input flake.

{
  neovim-flake = {
    url = github:notashelf/neovim-flake;
    # you can override input nixpkgs
    inputs.nixpkgs.follows = "nixpkgs";
    # you can also override individual plugins
    # i.e inputs.obsidian-nvim.follows = "obsidian-nvim"; # <- obsidian nvim needs to be in your inputs
  };
}

Followed by importing the home-manager module somewhere in your configuration.

{
  # assuming neovim-flake is in your inputs and inputs is in the argset
  imports = [ inputs.neovim-flake.homeManagerModules.default ];
}

An example installation for standalone home-manager would look like this:

{
  inputs = {
    nixpkgs.url = "github:NixOS/nixpkgs/nixos-unstable";
    home-manager.url = "github:nix-community/home-manager";
    stylix.url = "github:notashelf/neovim-flake";
  };

  outputs = { nixpkgs, home-manager, neovim-flake ... }: let
  system = "x86_64-linux"; in {
    # ↓ this is the home-manager output in the flake schema
    homeConfigurations."yourUsername»" = home-manager.lib.homeManagerConfiguration {
      pkgs = nixpkgs.legacyPackages.x86_64-linux;
      modules = [
        neovim-flake.homeManagerModules.default # <- this imports the home-manager module that provides the options
        ./home.nix # your home-manager configuration, probably where you will want to add programs.neovim-flake options
      ];
    };
  };
}

Once the module is imported, we will be able to define the following options (and much more) from inside the home-manager configuration.

  programs.neovim-flake = {

    enable = true;
    # your settings need to go into the settings attribute set
    # most settings are documented in the appendix
    settings = {
      vim.viAlias = false;
      vim.vimAlias = true;
      vim.lsp = {
        enable = true;
      };
    };
  };
}

Note

You may find all avaliable options in the appendix

Language Support

Language specific support means there is a combination of language specific plugins, treesitter support, nvim-lspconfig language servers, and null-ls integration. This gets you capabilities ranging from autocompletion to formatting to diagnostics. The following languages have sections under the vim.languages attribute. See the configuration docs for details.

Rust: vim.languages.rust.enable

Nix: vim.languages.nix.enable

SQL: vim.languages.sql.enable

C/C++: vim.languages.clang.enable

Typescript/Javascript: vim.languages.ts.enable

Python: vim.languages.python.enable:

Zig: vim.languages.zig.enable

Markdown: vim.languages.markdown.enable

HTML: vim.languages.html.enable

Dart: vim.languages.dart.enable

Go: vim.languages.go.enable

Lua: vim.languages.lua.enable

PHP: vim.languages.php.enable

Adding support for more languages, and improving support for existing ones are great places where you can contribute with a PR.

Table of Contents

LSP Custom Packages/Command

LSP Custom Packages/Command

In any of the opt.languages.<language>.lsp.package options you can provide your own LSP package, or provide the command to launch the language server, as a list of strings.

You can use this to skip automatic installation of a language server, and instead use the one found in your $PATH during runtime, for example:

vim.languages.java = {
  lsp = {
    enable = true;
    package = ["jdt-language-server" "-data" "~/.cache/jdtls/workspace"];
  };
}

Hacking neovim-flake

neovim-flake is designed for developers as much as it is for the end user. I would like any potential contributor to be able to propagate their desired changes into the repository without the extra effort. As such, below are guides (and guidelines) to streamline the contribution process and ensure that your valuable input seamlessly integrates into neovim-flake’s development without leaving question marks in your head.

This section is mainly directed towards those who wish to contribute code into neovim-flake. If you wish to instead report a bug or discuss a potential feature implementation, first look among the already open issues and if no matching issue exists you may open a new issue and describe your problem/request. While creating an issue, please try to include as much information as you can, ideally also include relevant context in which an issue occurs or a feature should be implemented.

Table of Contents

Getting Started
Guidelines
Testing Changes
Keybinds
Adding Plugins

Getting Started

You naturally would like to start by forking the repository. If you are new to git, have a look at GitHub’s Fork a repo guide for instructions on how you can do this. Once you have a fork of neovim-flake you should create a branch starting at the most recent main branch. Give your branch a reasonably descriptive name, suffixed by its type - i.e feature/debugger or fix/pesky-bug.

Implement your changes and commit them to the newly created branch and when you are happy with the result and positive that it fulfills Guidelines. Once you are confident everything is in order, push the branch to GitHub and create a pull request, following the template that you will be prompted to fill.

Guidelines

Adding Documentation
Formatting Code
Formatting Commits
Commit Style
Example Commit
Code Style

If your contribution tightly follows the guidelines, then there is a good chance it will be merged without too much trouble. Some of the guidelines will be strictly enforced, others will remain as gentle nudges towards the correct direction. As we have no automated system enforcing those guidelines, please try to double check your changes before making your pull request in order to avoid “faulty” code slipping by.

If you are uncertain how these rules affect the change you would like to make then feel free to start a discussion in the discussions tab ideally (but not necessarily) before you start developing.

Adding Documentation

Most, if not all, changes warrant changes to the documentation. Module options should be documented with Nixpkgs-flavoured Markdown, albeit with exceptions.

Note

As of v0.6, neovim-flake is itself documented using full markdown in both module options and the manual.

The HTML version of this manual containing both the module option descriptions and the documentation of neovim-flake (such as this page) can be generated and opened by typing the following in a shell within a clone of the neovim-flake Git repository:

$ nix build .#docs-html
$ xdg-open $PWD/result/share/doc/neovim-flake/index.html

Formatting Code

Make sure your code is formatted as described in code-style section. To maintain consistency throughout the project you are encouraged to browse through existing code and adopt its style also in new code.

Formatting Commits

Similar to code style guidelines we encourage a consistent commit message format as described in commit style guidelines.

Commit Style

The commits in your pull request should be reasonably self-contained. Which means each and every commit in a pull request should make sense both on its own and in general context. That is, a second commit should not resolve an issue that is introduced in an earlier commit. In particular, you will be asked to amend any commit that introduces syntax errors or similar problems even if they are fixed in a later commit.

The commit messages should follow the {seven-rules}[seven rules], except for “Capitalize the subject line”. We also ask you to include the affected code component or module in the first line. A commit message ideally, but not necessarily, follow the given template from home-manager’s own documentation

  {component}: {description}

  {long description}

where {component} refers to the code component (or module) your change affects, {description} is a very brief description of your change, and {long description} is an optional clarifying description. As a rare exception, if there is no clear component, or your change affects many components, then the {component} part is optional. See <<ex-commit-message>> for a commit message that fulfills these requirements.

Example Commit

The commit {example-commit-message}[69f8e47e9e74c8d3d060ca22e18246b7f7d988ef] contains the commit message

starship: allow running in Emacs if vterm is used

The vterm buffer is backed by libvterm and can handle Starship prompts
without issues.

Long description can be ommitted if the change is too simple to warrant it. A minor fix in spelling or a formatting change does not warrant long description, however, a module addition or removal does as you would like to provide the relevant context for your changes.

Finally, when adding a new module, say modules/foo.nix, we use the fixed commit format foo: add module. You can, of course, still include a long description if you wish.

In case of nested modules, i.e modules/languages/java.nix you are recommended to contain the parent as well - for example languages/java: some major change.

Code Style

Treewide Keep lines at a reasonable width, ideally 80 characters or less. This also applies to string literals and module descriptions and documentation.

Nix neovim-flake is formatted by the alejandra tool and the formatting is checked in the pull request and push workflows. Run the nix fmt command inside the project repository before submitting your pull request.

While Alejandra is mostly opinionated on how code looks after formatting, certain changes are done at the user’s discretion based on how the original code was structured.

Please use one line code for attribute sets that contain only one subset. For example:

# parent modules should always be unfolded
# which means module = { value = ... } instead of module.value = { ... }
module = {
  value = mkEnableOption "some description" // { default = true; }; # merges can be done inline where possible

    # same as parent modules, unfold submodules
    subModule = {
        # this is an option that contains more than one nested value
        someOtherValue = mkOption {
            type = lib.types.bool;
            description = "Some other description";
            default = true;
        };
    };
}

If you move a line down after the merge operator, Alejandra will automatically unfold the whole merged attrset for you, which we do not want.

module = {
  key = mkEnableOption "some description" // {
    default = true; # we want this to be inline
  }; # ...
}

For lists, it is mostly up to your own discretion how you want to format them, but please try to unfold lists if they contain multiple items and especially if they are to include comments.

# this is ok

acceptableList = [
  item1 # comment
  item2
  item3 # some other comment
  item4
];

# this is not ok
listToBeAvoided = [item1 item2 /* comment */ item3 item4];

# this is ok
acceptableList = [item1];

# this is not ok
listToBeAvoided = [
  item1
];

Testing Changes

Once you have made your changes, you will need to test them throughly. If it is a module, add your module option to configuration.nix (located in the root of this project) inside neovimConfiguration. Enable it, and then run the maximal configuration with nix run .#maximal -Lv to check for build errors. If neovim opens in the current directory without any error messages (you can check the output of :messages inside neovim to see if there are any errors), then your changes are good to go. Open your pull request, and it will be reviewed as soon as posssible.

If it is not a new module, but a change to an existing one, then make sure the module you have changed is enabled in the maximal configuration by editing configuration.nix, and then run it with nix run .#maximal -Lv. Same procedure as adding a new module will apply here.

Keybinds

Custom Key Mappings Support for a Plugin

As of 0.4, there exists an API for writing your own keybinds and a couple of useful utility functions are available in the https://github.com/NotAShelf/neovim-flake/tree/main/lib[extended standard library]. The following section contains a general overview to how you may utilize said functions.

Custom Key Mappings Support for a Plugin

:maps: https://notashelf.github.io/neovim-flake/options.html#opt-vim.maps.command.name.action

To set a mapping, you should define it in vim.maps.<<mode>>. The available modes are:

normal

insert

select

visual

terminal

normalVisualOp

visualOnly

operator

insertCommand

lang

command

An example, simple keybinding, can look like this:

{
  vim.maps.normal = {
    "<leader>wq" = {
      action = ":wq<CR>";
      silent = true;
      desc = "Save file and quit";
    };
  };
}

There are many settings available in the options. Please refer to the {maps}[documentation] to see a list of them.

neovim-flake provides a list of helper commands, so that you don’t have to write the mapping attribute sets every time:

mkBinding = key: action: desc: - makes a basic binding, with silent set to true.

mkExprBinding = key: action: desc: - makes an expression binding, with lua, silent, and expr set to true.

mkLuaBinding = key: action: desc: - makes an expression binding, with lua, and silent set to true.

Note that the Lua in these bindings is actual Lua, not pasted into a :lua command. Therefore, you either pass in a function like require('someplugin').some_function, without actually calling it, or you define your own function, like function() require('someplugin').some_function() end.

Additionally, to not have to repeat the descriptions, there’s another utility function with its own set of functions:

Utility function that takes two attrsets:

{ someKey = "some_value" }

{ someKey = { description = "Some Description"; }; }

and merges them into { someKey = { value = "some_value"; description = "Some Description"; }; }

addDescriptionsToMappings = actualMappings: mappingDefinitions:

This function can be used in combination with the same mkBinding functions as above, except they only take two arguments - binding and action, and have different names:

mkSetBinding = binding: action: - makes a basic binding, with silent set to true.

mkSetExprBinding = binding: action: - makes an expression binding, with lua, silent, and expr set to true.

mkSetLuaBinding = binding: action: - makes an expression binding, with lua, and silent set to true.

You can read the source code of some modules to see them in action, but their usage should look something like this:

# plugindefinition.nix
{lib, ...}: with lib; {
  options.vim.plugin = {
    enable = mkEnableOption "Enable plugin";

    # Mappings should always be inside an attrset called mappings
    mappings = {
      # mkMappingOption is a helper function from lib,
      # that takes a description (which will also appear in which-key),
      # and a default mapping (which can be null)
      toggleCurrentLine = mkMappingOption "Toggle current line comment" "gcc";
      toggleCurrentBlock = mkMappingOption "Toggle current block comment" "gbc";

      toggleOpLeaderLine = mkMappingOption "Toggle line comment" "gc";
      toggleOpLeaderBlock = mkMappingOption "Toggle block comment" "gb";

      toggleSelectedLine = mkMappingOption "Toggle selected comment" "gc";
      toggleSelectedBlock = mkMappingOption "Toggle selected block" "gb";
    };

  };
}

# config.nix
{
  pkgs,
  config,
  lib,
  ...
}:
  with lib;
  with builtins; let
    cfg = config.vim.plugin;
    self = import ./plugindefinition.nix {inherit lib;};
    mappingDefinitions = self.options.vim.plugin;

    # addDescriptionsToMappings is a helper function from lib,
    # that merges mapping values and their descriptions
    # into one nice attribute set
    mappings = addDescriptionsToMappings cfg.mappings mappingDefinitions;
in {
  config = mkIf (cfg.enable) {
    # ...
    vim.maps.normal = mkMerge [
      # mkSetBinding is another helper function from lib,
      # that actually adds the mapping with a description.
      (mkSetBinding mappings.findFiles "<cmd> Telescope find_files<CR>")
      (mkSetBinding mappings.liveGrep "<cmd> Telescope live_grep<CR>")
      (mkSetBinding mappings.buffers "<cmd> Telescope buffers<CR>")
      (mkSetBinding mappings.helpTags "<cmd> Telescope help_tags<CR>")
      (mkSetBinding mappings.open "<cmd> Telescope<CR>")

      (mkSetBinding mappings.gitCommits "<cmd> Telescope git_commits<CR>")
      (mkSetBinding mappings.gitBufferCommits "<cmd> Telescope git_bcommits<CR>")
      (mkSetBinding mappings.gitBranches "<cmd> Telescope git_branches<CR>")
      (mkSetBinding mappings.gitStatus "<cmd> Telescope git_status<CR>")
      (mkSetBinding mappings.gitStash "<cmd> Telescope git_stash<CR>")

      (mkIf config.vim.lsp.enable (mkMerge [
        (mkSetBinding mappings.lspDocumentSymbols "<cmd> Telescope lsp_document_symbols<CR>")
        (mkSetBinding mappings.lspWorkspaceSymbols "<cmd> Telescope lsp_workspace_symbols<CR>")

        (mkSetBinding mappings.lspReferences "<cmd> Telescope lsp_references<CR>")
        (mkSetBinding mappings.lspImplementations "<cmd> Telescope lsp_implementations<CR>")
        (mkSetBinding mappings.lspDefinitions "<cmd> Telescope lsp_definitions<CR>")
        (mkSetBinding mappings.lspTypeDefinitions "<cmd> Telescope lsp_type_definitions<CR>")
        (mkSetBinding mappings.diagnostics "<cmd> Telescope diagnostics<CR>")
      ]))

      (
        mkIf config.vim.treesitter.enable
        (mkSetBinding mappings.treesitter "<cmd> Telescope treesitter<CR>")
      )
    ];
    # ...
  };
}

Note

If you have come across a plugin that has an API that doesn’t seem to easily allow custom keybindings, don’t be scared to implement a draft PR. We’ll help you get it done.

Adding Plugins

To add a new neovim plugin, first add the source url in the inputs section of flake.nix

{
  inputs = {
    # ...
    neodev-nvim = {
      url = "github:folke/neodev.nvim";
      flake = false;
    };
    # ...
  };
}

Then add the name of the plugin into the availablePlugins variable in lib/types/plugins.nix:

# ...
availablePlugins = [
  # ...
  "neodev-nvim"
];

You can now reference this plugin using its string name:

config.vim.startPlugins = ["neodev-nvim"];

|   |  Next
  |   |  Appendix A. Neovim Flake Configuration Options